Guide to the Humanities Council Records, 1961 - 1979
Duke University. University Archives
Humanities Council records 1961 - 1979
Duke University. Humanities Council.
0.5 linear feet Extent: 500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
The Humanities Council of Duke University was created in 1961 to give attention to various matters affecting the humanities departments as a whole, including the advancement of research, interdepartmental and inter-institutional programs, and support for various humanistic activities. The Humanities Council records consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, clippings, and printed programs relating to planning, resource allocation, curriculum, and state of the humanities at Duke University from 1961 to 1979. Major subjects include graduate studies in anthropology, the Department of Music, the Museum of Art, medieval and renaissance studies, the American Comparative Literature Association, the Cooperative Program in the Humanities between Duke and the University of North Carolina, and the National Humanities Center. English.
UA.26.03.0009
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Humanities Council Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974 and 1978.
Historical Note
The Humanities Council of Duke University was originally constituted in 1961. Its function was to give attention to various matters affecting the Humanities departments as a whole, including the advancement of research, interdepartmental and inter-institution programs of lectures, exhibits, seminars, and the support for various humanistic activities. The committee was appointed by the President of the University and consisted of seven faculty members representing the departments of English, Religion, History, Romance Languages, Music, Art, and Philosophy. The first Chair of this committee was Arlin Turner, Professor of English.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of records relating to planning, resource allocation, curriculum, and state of the humanities at the University as dealt with by the Committee. Correspondence, memoranda, reports (typed and annotated), minutes, clipping, charts, projections, and printed programs comprise the bulk of this collection. There exist some materials that are not created out of the general functioning of the committee. These materials, while not being direct results of committee work, help to better understand the functioning and role of the Committee in the life of the University. These materials are mainly dedications programs and leaflets, reports, booklets, and reports from outside bodies, such as the American Comparative Literature Association.
Subject Headings
American Comparative Literature Association; Cooperative Program in the Humanities; Duke University -- Curricula; Duke University. Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies; Duke University -- Degrees; Duke University. Dept. of Cultural Anthropology; Duke University. Dept. of Music; Duke University. Humanities Council; Duke University. Museum of Art; Education, Humanistic; Humanities -- Research; Humanities -- Study and teaching; National Humanities Center; University cooperation; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- Curricula
Contents of Collection
- Minutes, 1963-1969
  Minutes of the Humanities Council chronicle the development of the humanities at Duke University. Here one can see the steps taken in the assessment, planning and implementation of the Humanities.
  - Minutes, December 1963-November 1969 (Box 1)
- Proposals, 1976 and undated (Box 1)
  This series contains humanities-related proposals from various bodies within the Committee and University.
  - Proposal for a Pilot Accelerated Ph.D. Program at Duke University, undated (Box 1)
  - Proposal to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation to Strengthen the Humanities at Duke University, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Program of Graduate Studies in Anthropology Leading to the M.A. and Ph.D. Degrees, undated (Box 1)
- Reports, 1961-1975, undated (Box 1)
  This series consists of reports produced by the committee and by outside groups closely associated with the workings of the committee.
  - Dept. of Music, 1961-1963, undated (Box 1)
  - Duke University Center for Studies in Humanities, undated (Box 1)
  - Duke University Museum of Art, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Questionnaire, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Council, 1963-1965, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Medieval and Renaissance Studies, undated (Box 1)
  - Professional Standards (American Comparative Literature Association), undated (Box 1)
- Printed Matter, 1967-1979. (Box 1)
  This series contains printed matter. Not all of the material within this series was produced by the committee, but it demonstrates the working of the committee with other bodies, both inside and outside the University.
  - Cooperative Program in the Humanities, University of North Carolina and Duke University, 1963-1964, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Program, Ground-Breaking Exercise, National Humanities Center, April 16, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Dedication of the National Humanities Center, April 7, 1979 (Box 1)